Burdick, Walton E. Papers 5937
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Walton E. Burdick Papers
1954-1993
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Burdick, Walton E.
5937
2.78 cubic feet
2.8 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
5736586
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 21, 2005
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 18, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Walton E. Burdick, IBM senior vice president, personnel, joined the company in Endicott in 1955.
He subsequently held personnel positions in Endicott, New York; Dayton, New Jersey; New York City and Greencastle, Indiana. In 1965, he was promoted to director of personnel relations, corporate headquarters, and in 1967, Mr. Burdick was named director of personnel, IBM World Trade Corporation. He was promoted to IBM director of personnel plans and programs in November 1970, and elected a vice president in June 1972. He was appointed assistant group executive, finance and planning, General Business Group, in August 1977. He was named IBM vice president, personnel in August 1980, and reports to Mr. John F. Akers, chairman of the board. In January 1989 he was appointed a member of IBM's Corporate Management Board and was elected an IBM senior vice president in April of the same year.
Mr. Burdick holds a B.S. Degree from the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University where he serves as a member of the Advisory Council. He was appointed by President Ronald Reagan for two terms as a commissioner on the National Commission for Employment Policy; and in January 1988 was appointed by President Reagan as a member of the White House Conference for a Drug Free America. He also serves on Secretary of Labor's Commission on Achieving Necessary Skills (SCANS). He is a member and past chairman of Cornell University's Advisory Board for the Center for Advanced Human Resource Studies and the Business Roundtable Employee Relations Committee. The Society for Human Resource Management (SHRM) selected him as the winner of the 1991 Award for Professional Excellence. He has also served on the National Board of Junior Achievement, the National Leadership Commission on Health Care, the Board of Directors of the National Alliance of Business, and is active in several professional organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5226: National Council On Household Employment Records
Arrangement
Series I: Speeches - Includes copies of speeches (and related documents) by W. E. Burdick, IBM Senior Vice-President
Series II: Interviews
Series III: Selected Planning Documents - Includes papers, charts and outlines used in making internal corporate presentations
Series IV: IBM Personnel Department. Related Documents - includes statements, memos, speeches, outlines and other material related to various functions of the IBM Personnel Department, 1988-1990
Series V: Publications
Series VI: Other
Sub-Series A. Miscellaneous: Articles, etc., 1989-1993 Sub-Series B. Audio-Visual Materials
Burdick, Walton E.; International Business Machines Corporation, Archives.
5736586
- Series Series I: Speeches - Includes copies of speeches (and related documents) by W. E. Burdick, IBM Senior Vice-President
  - "Impact/Influence: Defining and Charting a Course For Personnel Vitality.*, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Keynote speaker of the National Annual Meeting of the American Society for Personnel Administrators, San Diego, 6/2/76. 11 p.
  - IBM - A Great Place to Work., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    NAD Recognition Event Speech. 17 p.
  - "Closing Remarks.", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    National Personnel Managers Meeting, Nev Orleans, January 20, 1983. 13 p.
  - "Striving for Organizational and Individual Excellence In Management.", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Silver Bay Association Invitational Conference on Human Management Issues in Management, Lake George, 7/11/84. 19 p.
  - ISG National Meeting., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    New York, 9/23/86. 19 p.
  - Human Resources Forum., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    9/8/87. 11 p. and related documents.
  - Security Analysts Meeting., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    11/4/87. Unpaged.
  - Florida West Coast Retiree Luncheon, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    11/17/87. 11 p. and related documents.
  - International Personnel Managers Meeting., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2/88 (Includes related documents and copy of 1985 speech).
  - Human Resources Planning Society., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    3/28/88. 11 p. and related documents.
  - "A Personnel Overview.", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Wall Street Journal, Executive Visit, 4/18/88. Related documents.
  - "Strategic Meeting", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    includes "Introductory Comments" (6 p.) and "Leadership Study Comments" (3 p.), July 19-20, 1988.
  - "Burdick Transcript for IBM,", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    12/22/88 and related documents.
  - "Managing People Through a Period of Change.", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    The Conference Board. Key Issues in Human Resources Management: 2nd Annual West Coast Conference. 5/9/89. 14 p. (Includes tape of speech.)
  - "Do Compensation Policies Matter.", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Compensation and Firm Performance Conference. 5/23/89
  - IBM Personnel Institute., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    5/25/89. 13 p.
  - IBM International Personnel Institute., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    6/4/89. 16 p.
  - International Personnel Directors Meeting., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    9/13-15/89. Related documents.
  - IBM Personnel Institute., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    9/24/89. 17 p. Includes 39 pages of questions and answers.
  - University Human Resources PC Forum, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
    11/13-14/89. 9 p. Related documents.
  - Atlanta visit., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    December 5, 1989. 15 p. Related documents (includes tape of speech).
  - AMS Comments., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    7/24/90. Includes speech outline.
  - "U.S. Personnel Managers", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    1/22/91. Speech outline.
  - Michigan State., 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    4/18/91. Outline and related documents.
  - GTE Corp., 1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    5/15/91. Outline and related documents.
  - Undated and miscellaneous - (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Includes untitled speech, 25 p.; undated speech, "Full Employment Communication," 3 p.; and miscellaneous.
- Series Series II: Interviews
  - Interview with Karen Springer, Newsweek., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    2/12/88. 41 p.
  - Interview with Bart Ziegler, Associated Press, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    12/4/90. 24 p.
  - Interview with Carol Loomis. Fortune Magazine, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    6/4/91. 60 p.
  - Briefing Book for W.E. Burdick, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Interview with Fortune Magazine, David Kirkpatrick - Reporter, 5/21/92. (no transcript).
  - Briefing Book for Burdick, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Interview with NY Times. 6/3/92. (no transcript).
  - Interviews - Misc., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Walt Burdick, Don Devey, Leigh Faldi interviewed by Don Machy, 30 p. undated. Discussion joints, "Management "Project Report" Interview, 1/26/90 V no transcript.
- Series Series III: Selected Planning Documents - Includes papers, charts and outlines used in making internal corporate presentations
  - "Basic Strategic Directions for IBM Resources." (Box 1, Folder 36)
    undated.
  - Business Roundtable Education Initiative, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Corporate organization., 1954-1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Includes organization charts and chronology of major organization changes
  - Hong Kong, Singapore, Tokyo Visits, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes itineraries, country profiles, lists of key contacts and other related documents re meetings with IBM managers and others.
  - "Human Resource Planning and Technological Change.", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    February 1985.
  - "Human Resources in the 90's, A 1986 Perspective." (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "IBM...A Great Place to Work". (vs. Personnel Research), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    May 1991.
  - "IBM...A Special Place to Work"., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    July 1985.
  - IBM Overview (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - IBM Planning Process (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Personnel Managers Seminar, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    1/8/90.
  - Management Charts (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Market Driven Quality"., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Objectives., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes summary of corporate personnel staff's 1991 objectives.
  - Opinion Surveys in IBM - An Overview" (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "People management: A Guide for Managers"., 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    44 p.
  - Personnel Initiatives. Includes review of benefits (Box 2, Folder 13)
    1940's - 1990's.
  - "Personnel Management in IBM" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    undated. 31 p.
  - "Personnel Planning in IBM"., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Personnel Systems Support"., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Personnel Managers Meeting, 2/6/89.
  - "Planning In the IBM Corporation"., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Priorities For the Human Resource Function in the 1990's"., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Cornell University, April 9, 1991.
  - "Role of Personnel"., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "The Role of the First-Line Manager" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    n. d. 5 p.
  - "Staff Discussion Guide - Role of Personnel"., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    54 p.
  - "Uses of Information Technology"., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Work/Life Report", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series Series IV: IBM Personnel Department. Related Documents - includes statements, memos, speeches, outlines and other material related to various functions of the IBM Personnel Department, 1988-1990
  - A 21st Century Vision: A Worldwide Human Resource Study; The Evolution; Function and Scope of Personnel Administration; "Issues and Paradoxes in Human Resources, Midyear 1990," by Richard Beaumont; "Restructuring IBM Education" by Ursula F. Fairbairn; Spe, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
- Series Series V: Publications
  - Issues of IBM Personnel Forum which includes "Letter from the Senior Vice-President, Personnel" Walt Burdick., 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Articles written about W.E. Burdick which appeared in Personnel Administrator, Think, Society for Human Resource Management/Conference Daily. HR News., 1976- 1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Secretary's Commission on Achieving Necessary Skills (SCANS). Walton E. Burdick, member., 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
    Includes reports and publications of the Commission.
- Series Series VI: Other
  - Sub-Series A. Miscellaneous: Articles, etc., 1989-1993
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence., 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
      Includes correspondence with Professor Lee Dyer and Professor Maurice Neufeld of NYSSILR, Cornell University concerning Burdick's participation in the School's 50th Anniversary publication, with Lee Dyer of Cornell's Center for Advanced Human Resource Stu
  - Sub-Series B. Audio-Visual Materials
    - "Opportunity 2000" Award Presentation for IBM Personnel. "Our Changing Work Force.", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      11/15/88 (Video Cassette) 9 minutes.
    - "Role of Personnel" Produced by IBM Corporation. Personnel Plans and Programs. (Box 2, Folder 34)
      (Video Cassette) 22 minutes.
    - Burdick - San Diego, 1984 (Box 3)
      (Audio cassette).
    - Burdick - Nashville, 1985 (Box 4)
      (Audio Cassette).
    - Burdick - 1986 SWMD Hundred Percent Club, Phoenix, AZ. (Box 5)
    - Burdick - Challenges and Creative Responses, 1986 (Box 6)
      6/86 (Audio Cassette).
    - Burdick - APG Golden Circle, 1989 (Box 7)
      6/8/89 (Audio Cassette).
    - Burdick - Cornell Speech, 1989 (Box 8)
      8/24/89. (Audio Cassette).
    - Executive Conference (Box 9)
      (no date) (Audio Cassette).